MacKaye Family papers ML-5
Rauner Special Collections Library
MacKaye Family papers
1751-1998
Rauner Special Collections Library
MacKaye Family
ML-5
561 linear ft. 380 boxes
The MacKaye Family Papers contain correspondence, manuscript drafts, photographs, financial records, sketchbooks, notebooks, diaries, programs, broadsides, posters, newspaper clippings, and ephemeral items. They chronicle four generations of the family. The bulk of the collections focus is on dramatist Steele MacKaye, his son and fellow dramatist and poet, Percy Mackaye, as well as the noted conservationist Benton Mackaye.
Scope and Contents
The MacKaye Family Papers contain materials documenting the life and career of four generations of the family. They include a large amount of personal and professional correspondence as well as original manuscripts and typescripts of plays, prose, masques, pageants, poetry, essays and articles. Of note are manuscript materials for Benton MacKaye’s works on geotechnics entitled “Geotechnics of North America,” and “From Geography to Geotechnics,” as well as Percy MacKaye’s biography and works on his father Steele MacKaye and the MacKaye family, entitled respectively, “Epoch,” and “Annals of an Era.” In addition, there are numerous scrapbooks and photographs chronicling the development and creation of Steele and Percy MacKaye’s public and private theatrical productions. Steele MacKaye’s role as a dramatist, theater manager and inventor is evidenced through original broadsides, posters and documents relating to the Lyceum Theatre School of Acting, Francois Delsarte acting method, and MacKaye’s Madison Square Theatre in New York. Mackaye’s technical contributions to the theatre are shown through patent documents. A large amount of manuscript materials for Percy MacKaye’s dramatic works and publications are included as well as personal correspondence, financial records, business correspondence, programs, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, articles, photographs, theatrical stills and scrapbooks. Benton Mackaye’s role as a forester and conservationist is recorded through writings, bills, reports and charts of the many projects on natural resource planning he was involved with, such as the creation of the Appalachian Trail and the Tennessee Valley Authority. The collection also includes documentation of Benton’s work for the US Government in both the Department of Labor and Forest Service. Many of these activities and interests are shown through newspaper and journal clippings, notes and notebooks as well as legal and financial documents, flyers, pamphlets, bulletins, journals, sketches and ephemeral materials. The collection also includes a significant amount of material, private as well as professional, by Percy’s wife Marion Morse MacKaye and his mother Mary Medbery MacKaye, as well as his children, Arvia, Robert Keith and Christy and disparate family members and spouses. Among these materials are drawings, sketches, paintings, writings, and teaching materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Unrestricted.
MacKaye Family
Biography
The MacKaye family papers at Dartmouth College comprise materials for four generations of the family beginning with James Morrison Mackaye (1805-1888), an organizer of The Wells Fargo Express Company, and president of The American Telegraph Company during Abraham Lincoln's administration. However, the collection’s bulk begins with his son, Steele MacKaye, who was born in 1842 in Buffalo, New York. In 1858 Steele became a student of the 'Theatre Français' and studied at L’Ecole des Beaux Arts in Paris. In 1862 he returned home and enlisted in New York’s Seventh Regiment. Having married Mary Medbery, his second wife, in 1865, he continued his studies in Paris under the tutelage of Francois Delsarte. Between 1872-1894 he wrote thirty plays and acted in seventeen different roles. In 1873 he became the first American to play Hamlet in London. He also patented over 100 theatrical inventions between 1879-1893, including the folding theatre chair. His crowning piece would have been his “Spectatorium.” Planned to include twenty-five moving stages and seat 12,000 people, it was to be staged at the 1893 World’s Fair in Chicago. However, financial difficulties prevented the completion of the project. Steele MacKaye died in 1894. Also part of this generation, and represented to a lesser degree in the collection are Steele’s siblings; Sarah MacKaye Alling (1809-1904), Emily MacKaye von Hesse (1838-?), Sarah MacKaye Warner (1840-1876), his half brothers William Henry MacKaye (1834-1888) and Henry Goodwin MacKaye (1856-1913). Steele’s wife Mary Medbery MacKaye (1845-1924), was an author of a popular dramatization of Jane Austin’s “Pride and Prejudice“ and also has material in the collection. In addition, there are documents related to Mary Medbery’s first cousin and adopted sister Sarah Stetson Pevear (1831-1905). Steele MacKaye had seven children, Arthur Loring MacKay (1863-1939), Harold Steele (1866-1928), William Payson (1868-1889), James Medbery (1872-1935), Percy (1875-1956), Benton (1879-1975), and Hazel (1880-1944). Although all of them are represented in this collection the majority of the materials relate to Percy and Benton MacKaye. Born in 1875 in New York, Percy attended Harvard College, graduating in 1897. The following year he married Marion Morse and from 1898-1900 they lived abroad in Rome, Switzerland, and Germany, where he studied at the University of Leipzig. From 1900-1904 he taught at the Craigie School for Boys in New York and from 1906-1913 he lectured on theatre at Harvard, Yale, Columbia and other universities. In 1924 he received an honorary Ph.D. in Literature from Miami University in Ohio. He began to write seriously in 1905 and produced many pageants, plays, poems and essays. In 1927 he completed “Epoch,” a two volume biography of his father Steele, and after joining the MacDowell Colony in Peterborough, New Hampshire in 1930 he completed the work “Annals of an Era, Percy MacKaye and the MacKaye Family, 1826-1932.” In 1948 he received the Fellowship Award of the Academy of American Poets. Percy died on August 31, 1956 in Cornish, New Hampshire. There are also a number of manuscripts related to Percy’s wife Marion Morse MacKaye (1872-1939), including many commemorative poems and writings. Percy’s younger brother Benton was born March 8, 1879 in Stamford, Connecticut. He graduated from Harvard in 1900 and continued his education at Harvard Forestry School from which he graduated in 1905. He joined the US Forest Service in 1905 and the US Department of Labor in 1918. From 1920-1922 he worked on projects related to regional planning, during which he formulated the idea and plan for the Appalachian Trail. In 1928 he published his first book, “The New Exploration.” In 1933 he continued his work on preservation and planning as a consultant for the US Indian Service on Indian reservations in South Dakota, New Mexico and Arizona, and from 1934-1936 he was on the planning staff of the Tennessee Valley Authority. In 1937, he developed a plan for the development of the Bay Circuit Project in Massachusetts, and from 1938-1939 he was a consultant on flood control policies of the US Forest Service. In 1940 he began his study of conservation with population distribution for the US Forest Service and continued in 1942 with a formulated proposal for the “Alaska-Siberia Burma Road.” From 1942-1945 he was a member of the Rural Electrification Administration. He retired in 1945. After his retirement, he published a collection of thirteen of his essays entitled “From Geography to Geotechnics,” in 1968. He also began work on his last book “Geotechnics of North America,” which he never finished. Benton MacKaye died on December 11, 1975. A small part of this collection pertains to Benton’s wife, Jesse Bell Hardy Stubbs MacKaye (1875-1921), a devoted suffragette. The youngest of Steele’s children, Hazel MacKaye was born on August 24, 1880 and was named after the character “Hazel Kirke” in one of her father’s plays by the same name. In 1910 she was made an honorary member of Radcliffe College’s graduating class. From 1911-1917 she designed, directed and wrote many pageants and acted in a few of her father’s as well. In 1924 she wrote “The Enchanted Urn,” a fantasy in pantomime. She died in Westport, Connecticut in 1944. The remainder of the collection is related to Percy’s children Robert Keith (Robin) MacKaye (1899-1992), a sketch artist; Arvia MacKaye (1902- 1989), a poet and founder of the Rudolph Steiner Educational and Farming Association and Christy MacKaye ( 1909-2002 ), who published her first book of poetry when she was twenty-one. Christy was devoted to anthroposophy and trained in speech and drama at the Goetheanum in Dornach, Switzerland. She also taught English for many years at the Rudolf Steiner School in New York.
- Addendum 2, 1751-1990; 24
  Conditions Governing Access
  Unrestricted.
  General
  This series: formerly UP-6
  Scope and Contents
  Addendum
  - Contains the final version of “Percy Mackaye, A Bibliographic Biography,” along with extensive p..., 1930-1932 (Box 326)
    Unrestricted
    Contains the final version of “Percy Mackaye, A Bibliographic Biography,” along with extensive proofs and revisions from over the course of a few years. Also, the box contains magazines and journals that published Mackaye’s work or published work about Mackaye, such as “Survey Graphic,” “Scholastic,” “The Drama Magazine,” “Harpers,” A Living Theatre,” “The Mask, “Theatre Arts Monthly,” “The American Oxonian,” “Caliban,” “Theatre Magazine,” and “The Virginia Quarterly Review.” The box also contains information concerning Mackaye’s Phi Beta Kappa standing at Harvard and a Harvard graduate magazine.
  - Contains two manuscripts, “Uncle John Fiddler and Cutshin Trip” and “Diary of Marion Mackaye: Pi..., 1899-1937 (Box 327)
    Contains two manuscripts, “Uncle John Fiddler and Cutshin Trip” and “Diary of Marion Mackaye: Pine Mountain Summer, 1921,” which highlight the Mackaye’s trip to Kentucky Mountain. There is a scrapbook of the Kentucky Mountain travels accompanying these manuscripts. Also, the box contains Arvia Mackaye’s passport, a copy of “The Evidence of Immortality” by Jerome Anderson from 1899, assorted plays by Anne Hempstead Branch and collection of linoleum printing plates. Furthermore, the box generally contains correspondence, published writings in newspapers and otherwise about Mackaye, poetry in Mackaye’s hand, photographs, and Mackaye’s personal notebooks.
  - Contains a preliminary manuscript to Percy Mackaye’s autobiography, typed and in his own hand. ..., 1921-1956 (Box 328)
    Contains a preliminary manuscript to Percy Mackaye’s autobiography, typed and in his own hand. Also, the box contains assorted playbills from live performances of Mackaye’s works along with a compilation of journals and publications with articles concerning or by Percy Mackaye and other members of his family and manuscripts of poetry and plays by Arvia Mackaye, Percy Mackaye and Christy Mackaye, along with others. The box also contains a few personal notebooks of Percy Mackaye in his own hand, interviews from the Kentucky Mountain trip, a manuscript concerning civic theatre partly edited by Mackaye and general personal and professional correspondence concerning a wide variety of subjects. Finally, the box contains a manuscript of “Thoughts of her Friends,” by Marion Mackaye, 1939-1940.
  - Contains the “Diary-Journals” of “Marion, Morse, Mackaye” in two sets. One set of 10 volumes th..., 1898-1937 (Box 329)
    Contains the “Diary-Journals” of “Marion, Morse, Mackaye” in two sets. One set of 10 volumes that spans the years of 1898 to 1918. And a second incomplete set of two volumes that spans the years of 1933 to 1937. There is also a copy of Hamlet with marks and comments in by Percy Mackaye in his own hand.
  - Contains an assortment of miscellaneous letters, manuscripts and other items. Included are prof..., 1900-1950 (Box 330)
    Contains an assortment of miscellaneous letters, manuscripts and other items. Included are professional and personal correspondence particularly in related to the donation of PM’s papers to Harvard and Princeton Universities. Other items are personal photographs and letters and drafts and notes related to PM’s biography of his parents. Last, the papers contain manuscripts and correspondence with contemporary American authors; among these documents are a speech for the commemoration for Mrs. Mackaye, German translation of “Poog’s Pasture” and a copy of “My Lady Dear, Arise!, Poems: 1939.”
  - Contains diary journals of Marion Morse Mackaye (MMM) and correspondence with publishers about t..., 1898-1950 (Box 331)
    Contains diary journals of Marion Morse Mackaye (MMM) and correspondence with publishers about the “Kentucky Mountain Notes”. Also in the papers is correspondence with family and friends.
  - Contains notebooks with manuscripts, literature awards, scholarly notes, manuscripts of plays, n..., 1896-1950 (Box 332)
    Contains notebooks with manuscripts, literature awards, scholarly notes, manuscripts of plays, newspaper clippings containing reviews of t works and professional correspondence. Drafts include:the 1948 Fellowship Award of the Academy of American Poets, “A Garland to Sylvia”, “Fairness Found Out”,“The Swinging Doors” A Play in one act by Steele Mackaye, “My Catch-All: II”, ”Memorial Letters: Marion’s Volume”, “The Hour is Now!”, “What We Will”, “Through Death, Alive”, “A Colossal Confrontation with the Past”, “In Another Land”, “The Life-story of Percy and Marion Mackaye”, “My Love was Freshly Come from Sea”, “Champions of Creative Imagination”, “A Poet in Public Affairs”, “Art for and by the People” and “God, Humanity and the Mountains”.
  - Contains a book of letters addressed to Marion Mackaye, a notebook with poems, “Pine Mountain Ma..., 1920-1955 (Box 333)
    Contains a book of letters addressed to Marion Mackaye, a notebook with poems, “Pine Mountain Manual: Kentucky Mountain Notes, 1921”, 9 notebooks with notes, and photographs.
  - Contains a series of folders that contain PM’s personal papers. Included are personal and profe..., 1856-1955 (Box 334)
    Contains a series of folders that contain PM’s personal papers. Included are personal and professional correspondence, notes, reviews and articles of his Hamlet-inspired play, miscellaneous manuscripts, reviews and clippings of his Caliban masque, “discarded” manuscripts and works and notebooks of Steel MacKaye that contain aphorisms, addresses, calendars and dramatic manuscripts.
  - Contains papers concerning PM’s professional matters. Also included are manuscripts of poems, a..., 1871-1956 (Box 335)
    Contains papers concerning PM’s professional matters. Also included are manuscripts of poems, a copy of “The Palmetto Derby and other short stories” by George Hoyt Smith, a notebook by James Steele Mackaye “A Cure for Coquetry” original manuscript, a notebook containing the original manuscript of “Marriage” by James Steele Mackaye, a notebook with “Silas Mariner” manuscript, a notebook of “But a Player” manuscript, and a notebook with untitled play manuscript by JS Mackaye
  - Contains much of the preparatory work and drafts of PM’s Hamlet tetralogy. Other items include ..., 1926-1956 (Box 336)
    Contains much of the preparatory work and drafts of PM’s Hamlet tetralogy. Other items include noteboooks with manuscripts of poems, photographs, personal correspondence, published poems and articles (e.g. Survey Graphic Magazines “Poetry of the Wild Trails” and “Untamed America” by Percy Mackaye). letters and clippings related to Percy Mackaye’s funeral and scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings, correspondence, bulletins, and pamphlets.
  - Contains notes related to the biography of PM’s parents that he was writing. Also among these p..., 1896-1956 (Box 337)
    Contains notes related to the biography of PM’s parents that he was writing. Also among these papers are PM’s published works: “Johnny Crimson: A Legend of Hollis Hall”, “On with the New Life,” Childhood”, “Father and Son”, and “Youth”.
  - Contains PM’s handscript works. Among the items are notebooks, journals, diaries, poems, plays,..., 1913-1956 (Box 338)
    Contains PM’s handscript works. Among the items are notebooks, journals, diaries, poems, plays, manuscripts, and correspondence. A binder labelled “Important leters: Important People and PMK” and a file box containing correspondence from 1930's are also in the box.
  - Contains correspondence, poems, photographs, and manuscripts of Steel Mackaye, PM and MMM. Othe..., 1882-1953 (Box 339)
    Contains correspondence, poems, photographs, and manuscripts of Steel Mackaye, PM and MMM. Other items are the hard bound books “Annals of an Era: Percy Mackaye and the Mackaye Family 1826-1932”, “Age of Fable or Beauties of Mythology” by Thomas Bulfinch, “The Sequestered Shrine: ‘Arvia’” “Percy Mackaye: A symposium on his Fiftieth Birthday 1925” “My Dear Lady, Arise!: Poems 1939” “Poem-Leaflets” “Poog’s Pasture: The Mythology of a Child” (multiple bound, corrected copies of the manuscript) “Journal of Marion Morse Mackaye: 1 jan 1938-22 May 1939” and “Emma: A Dramatization of Jane Austen’s Novel” by MMM (2 copies).
  - Contains letter boxes with photographs and very early correspondence of Steele Mackaye., 1884, undated (Box 340)
    Contains letter boxes with photographs and very early correspondence of Steele Mackaye.
  - Contains copies of poems, newspaper and press clippings related to PM’s poems., 1936-1954 (Box 341)
    Contains copies of poems, newspaper and press clippings related to PM’s poems.
  - Contains bound books. The titles include: “Peter Dale’s Garden” “Beowulf” “Johnny Crimson: A Le..., 1895-1924 (Box 342)
    Contains bound books. The titles include: “Peter Dale’s Garden” “Beowulf” “Johnny Crimson: A Legend of Hollis Hall” “Five One-Act Plays: 1899-1903” “Poems: Unpublished 1896-1915” “Various Uncollected Poems: Unpublished and Published From about 1897 to about 1924” “Sonnets” “Anti-Matrimony” “Fenris Der Wolf” “Die Vogelscheuche” “”L’Epouvantail” and “The Writings of William Payson Mackaye“
  - Contains bound manuscripts. The titles include: “Poems Copy 1: Apr. 1946-Sept. 1949” “Poems Cop..., 1939-1950 (Box 343)
    Contains bound manuscripts. The titles include: “Poems Copy 1: Apr. 1946-Sept. 1949” “Poems Copy 3: Feb ‘48-Aug. ‘50” “Poems 1939-1946” “Canvas notebook - 1940-1942” “Canvas Notebooks - Prose” “Copy #I - Sept ‘49-Jan ‘50” “Nov ‘47-Feb ‘48 (Original) Copy I” “Jan - Apr ‘54” “Aug 53” “Marion Copy 2” “Canvas Notebooks Marion”
  - Contains bound copies of manuscripts, a painting of PM, half-filled notebooks, a video reel, pro..., 1751-1953 (Box 344)
    Contains bound copies of manuscripts, a painting of PM, half-filled notebooks, a video reel, programs, correspondence related to PM’s literature and various photographs. The titles of the manuscripts include: “Rememberings: 1895-1945” “What is She? A Sonnet of Sonnets to Marion Morse” “From the Journal of Marion Morse MacKay 1907-1908”, “Cases of Conscience” book of Elizabeth MacKay, “Gospel Sonnets” “The History of the State and Sufferings of the Church of Scotland from the Restoration to the Revolution” “Poems Copy 3 - 46-50” “Copy Poems Jan 50-Aug 50” “Poems Copy #1: July 50-April 51” and “L’Epouvantail”.
  - Contains a series of magazines, journals, newspaper clippings, dramatic programs and photographs..., 1927-1959 (Box 345)
    Contains a series of magazines, journals, newspaper clippings, dramatic programs and photographs of the deceased PM. Most of the articles are reviews of PM’s literature, particularly the Hamlet tetralogy. Also included are memoirs and other information related to PM’s seventieth birthday, poems, family correspondence, and financial documents related to the sale of PM’s literature.
  - Contains clippings, theatrical programs, a songbook (“The Canterbury Pilgrims”), professional co..., 1899-1984 (Box 346)
    Contains clippings, theatrical programs, a songbook (“The Canterbury Pilgrims”), professional correspondence, a dramatic manuscript (“Fenris, Der Wolf”), copies of “Driftwind” journal, notebooks in German, and other articles and papers related to the production of PM’s plays and masques.
  - Contains old letters and photographs of the members of the Mackaye family. Included is a scroll..., 1868-1949 (Box 347)
    Contains old letters and photographs of the members of the Mackaye family. Included is a scroll of text and pictures, postcards, glass plates, rehearsal tickets, admission cards, a University of Oklahoma student paper on the “Kentucky Mountain Cycle,” and manuscripts from family members.
  - Contains unbound manuscripts: “Marion Mores Mackaye, Diary-Journal XIV 1922-1925” “Marion Morse ..., 1944-1990 (Box 348)
    Contains unbound manuscripts: “Marion Mores Mackaye, Diary-Journal XIV 1922-1925” “Marion Morse Mackaye, Diary-Journal 1915-1918” “Marion Morse Mackaye, Diary-Journal 1921-1922”; a working copy of “The Ghost of Elsinore: Hamlet, King of Denmark - Or What We Will” “The Serpent in the Orchard: Hamlet, King of Denmark - Or What We Will”; “What We Will: A Dramatic Saga”, an essay about PM’s tetralogy, “God, Humanity and the Mountains” “My Love Was Freshly Come from Sea”. Also included are correspondence and drafts of Arvia Mackaye’s biography of her father, PM, and mother, MMM.
  - Contains a copy of the hamlet tetralogy and a binder entitled “LETTERS: Marion Morse and Percy M..., 1896-1948 (Box 349)
    Contains a copy of the hamlet tetralogy and a binder entitled “LETTERS: Marion Morse and Percy Mackaye, Set I”.
  - Contains the first carbon copies of the Diary-Journals of MMM., 1898-1922 (Box 350)
    Contains the first carbon copies of the Diary-Journals of MMM.
  - Contains manuscripts of poems and PM’s last notebooks. These notebooks are entitled “Z”, ”V”, “..., 1947-1956 (Box 351)
    Contains manuscripts of poems and PM’s last notebooks. These notebooks are entitled “Z”, ”V”, “U” “W”, “Miscellaneous Typed Poems”, “Large Notebook Y” and its “insert”, “Catch-all”, “Large Notebook X”, and “Notes About Harvard Collection”. Also in this box is “The Miami” journal containing a poem by Arvia Mackaye amd a folder containing autobiographical notes of PM.
  - Contains photographs, pastel drawings, pencil sketches, copies of architectural plans, and photo..., 1871-1948 (Box 352)
    Contains photographs, pastel drawings, pencil sketches, copies of architectural plans, and photostats of books principally related to Percy Mackaye and the theatre.
  - Box: 353, 1909-1917 (Box 353)
    Box: 353
    - The Pilgrim and the Book Theatre Poster, undated (Box 353, Folder 1)
    - Dry Mounted photograph of Shakespeare statue in Central Park (386th anniversary of Shakespeare's birthday), undated (Box 353, Folder 2)
    - Dry mounted hand colored photograph of "The Wonderful 'Merrie England' scene of scene from 'Caliban'", undated (Box 353, Folder 3)
    - "The Scarecrow" theatre poster drawn by Gluyas Williams, 1909 (Box 353, Folder 4)
    - "E.R. Southern and Julia Marlow Repertoire" broadside, 1906 (Box 353, Folder 5)
    - "The Shakespeare Masque" theatre poster, 1916 (Box 353, Folder 6)
    - Photograph of cast and spectators at the Masque of St. Louis, 1914 (Box 353, Folder 7)
    - "The Pageant and Masque of St Loius" theatre poster, 1914 (Box 353, Folder 8)
    - "Caliban" at Harvard Stadium - poster, 1917 (Box 353, Folder 9)
  - Contains one charcoal drawing on fiberboard by Norman Bel Geddes. 29” x 29”, 1927 (Box 354)
    Contains one charcoal drawing on fiberboard by Norman Bel Geddes. 29” x 29”
  - Contains one oversize black and white photograph (21.5” x 50.5”). “An Audience of 150,000 at an ..., undated (Box 355)